Hi.
Melvin asked me on Twitter
...if it is possible to make a bracelet
...that removes the static electricity
from body and avoids shock.
Of course, there are these
...straps that ground the body
and remove static electricity.
But is it possible to make a cordless one?
And surely after I did a quick search,
...I found that there are these anti-static
cordless bracelets like these,
And my reaction was,
...well,
'These are scam!'
I mean, how can you remove static electricity
from your body without sending it any...
...in your back and put it in your pocket, you have to...
How do these things sell on the web?
...under those, people are having...
I mean, how does it work? It is not even...
See, every time your body picks up static electricity,
...say by walking with socks on the carpet,
The only way to get rid of them
...is to take them and put them somewhere else,
...like in the ground.
And that's what this wire does.
You can't just put those charges in a
container and keep them in your pocket!
Dave Jones from the channel
...which is a great electronics teardown,
review and debunk channel,
...has a great video about this
...and shows that these cordless bracelets are garbage.
Basically, they've showed the fake bracelet he got online
...contained only a single 1-MΩ resistor in it:
"And..."
"That's it!"
"Wow."
What's the use of that?
Is holding a resistor in my hands supposed
to magically discharge my body?
It is very important to at least understand
the tools you want to use for your work
...and educate yourself and not get scammed.
That's why this video is sponsored by:
A great website where you can find online
courses and learn whatever you like
...from a list of over 23,000 classes to choose from
...for as low as $10 a month.
But wait!
Oh, you're actually waiting?
And the first 500 people to use my promo code here
...get two months of free Skillshare premium.
Check it out!
Anyway,
...holding a 1-MΩ resister does nothing.
Why even 1 MΩ when you can hold a 0 Ω screwdriver?
Hmm...
That gives me an idea.
I was wondering if it is possible at all
...to have a standalone bracelet
that would dissipate charges.
And one thing came to mind, which is one of those
...punk rock bracelets with a bunch of spikes on them.
You might already know that
...electric charges accumulate on
the sharp points in a conductor,
And so much charge in a tiny point
...results in them repelling each other hard
...and dissipate into the air and environment.
You can easily see this when I run my Tesla coil.
See, the charges go out only from the
tip of the needle and nowhere else!
So I thought with those punk bracelets
having so many metal spikes,
...they potentially dissipate charges into the air quicker
...and drop my body voltage and reduce
the risk of discharge and shock.
So here's the plan.
I'm gonna buy one of those bracelets,
And to test it,
...I'm going to charge myself using my Van de Graaff
...and see if those spikes have any effect at all.
Granville Street in downtown Vancouver
...is one of those streets you can
find some questionable stores in.
Hopefully I can find what I need there.
'Fantasy Factory', eh?
Let's check that-
Jeez, that was the wrong shop.
Let's check the 'Rock Shop'.
Hopefully this one has it.
This looks like the right store.
Oh, there we are.
Those are the kind of spikes I'm looking for,
...but in a wrist band.
That's- What is that?
A collar or something?
I bought these two for a total of $70.
That's a strange expense on my business card.
Well, I got this not-very-impressive
one-row-of-spikes bracelet,
...but it's the pointiest one they had,
And then I found this one which is much pointier.
It's called 'The Choker',
...and they both have metal exposed
on the back to touch my skin.
Okay, let's do it without the spikes first.
I put my legs up,
...charge my body a little bit,
...and then discharge.
That was painful.
Okay,
...let's do it with the spikes now.
Okay, this time with the bracelet.
One,
...two,
...three,
...four,
...five
...and discharge.
It's absolutely useless.
Well, maybe the dome is charging my body too quickly.
So let's do it more realistically.
I'm gonna touch the dome,
...charge my body first,
...and then let go and then touch the ground.
I hate surprises.
Okay without the bracelet.
Charging my body.
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5,
...and discharge.
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5.
And now with the bracelet.
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5,
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5.
Useless.
Maybe it's not making a good contact to my body
...due to my massive fur,
So I'm gonna use aluminum foil
...to make sure that sparks are in good
contact with each other and my body.
Here we go.
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5,
And 1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5.
Useless!
F*** it.
Let's use 'The Choker'.
It's not gonna look good around your neck in the lab,
...so I'm gonna put it around my wrist
...with the foil around it for good contact.
If this doesn't do it, nothing will!
Here you go.
The super-duper anti-static bracelet!
Okay.
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5.
And 1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
What the hell?
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5,
1,
...2,
...3,
...4
Completely useless!
I really thought this would do it.
I really thought having spikes on your body should help,
...but maybe their effect is insignificant
...compared to how your body already
dissipates charges on its own.
Now let's put on the grounding strap
...and see how well that works.
1,
...2,
...3,
...4,
...5.
1,
...2,
...3
Nothing.
Even having my hand completely on the dome,
...I don't feel any discharge!
Now instead of this strap,
...I put my bare feet on the tiled ground.
See?
Even the non-conductive piles
...discharge better than those stupid spikes.
Well, you know what it means.
If these spikes can't discharge you faster
than your body's normal discharge rate,
...then there is nothing out there that
can discharge you cordlessly.
All those cordless anti-static
straps are just a pile of junk!
One note is that, even in the corded straps,
...there is a 1-MΩ resistance
in series with the grounding wire.
You never want to directly connect your body to ground,
...because in case you accidentally touch
high voltage you can easily get electrocuted.
The 1 MΩ limits the current and saves you
...while it's good enough to get rid of static charges.
So make sure you have a properly
grounded anti-static wristband,
...or risk killing your naked electronics.
And start learning new things at Skillshare!
And make sure to use the promo code.
Only the first 500 people to sign up
...get the two-month free access to all the courses
...so you don't have any excuse not to learn.
I personally like to pick up my
video-editing skills a notch
...because it's taking forever as is.
There is this course on Adobe Premiere
...and it seems the entire course
is less than three hours?
I can't take a lot of free courses in two months.
Am I allowed to use that promo code?
Ah, I'll just ask one of my cousins to sign up for me.
Oh
Get it before my cousins take all the spots.
Subtitles/captions by Jonathan Lee (Pentameron)
youtube.com/c/PentameronSV